You've paid Spotify more money every single year since
2023. And artists are getting paid less
per stream than ever. Let me say that again, because it should be the most
insane sentence in the music industry, and somehow nobody
talks about it. You, the listener, are paying more for
Spotify today than you have ever paid in the company's 18-year history.
Spotify raised its prices in 2023.
Then again in 2024. Then again in 2025,
and they just announced another hike for 2026.
Same app, same songs, same skip button. 4 price
increases in 4 years. And the people who actually made
the music, the artists whose songs you press play on every single
day, are watching their per-stream payout collapse. The math
is not complicated. You pay more, they get less.
Spotify keeps the difference, If that sounds like a scam, it's because
it is. It's just a very polite one, with a green logo and
a year-end wrapped slideshow. So today we're going to do something nobody
at Spotify wants you to do. We're going to read the receipt.
All of it. Where the money goes. Why artists are quitting.
Why the app you open every morning has gotten measurably
worse. Why Spotify spent a billion dollars on podcasts and then
walked away. Why they invented a fake number to make
their payouts look bigger, and why the founder of the company is currently
selling shares to go build weapons in Europe while the
platform that made him a billionaire quietly decays.
This is not a hit piece. This is an audit. And it starts
with the simplest question in the world: Where did your $11.99
actually go last month? Let's walk through the receipts.
2021. Spotify Premium in the US: costs $9.99.
It had cost $9.99 since 2014.
7 years, zero increases. That was the deal.
You pay $10, you get every song ever recorded,
ad-free, on every device. Spotify was the
best deal in tech. Honestly? Maybe the best
deal in the history of consumer media. $10 for the entire history
of recorded music in your pocket. Insane. June 2023.
First hike. $10.99.
Spotify blamed market conditions, said it
was the first increase in the company's history. True, market conditions
were a convenient excuse, but the real reason was simpler: they had
run out of new subscribers to acquire, and Wall Street demanded
growth. So they started squeezing the ones they already had. April 2024.
Second hike. $11.99.
One year later. This time they didn't even bother with a real
excuse. They just called it expansion of features.
You know what features they were talking about? Audiobooks.
15 hours of audiobooks per month.
Which you didn't ask for. Which most of you have never used.
Which they added to your plan whether you wanted it or not so they could
justify charging you another dollar. That's not a feature.
That's a hostage. July 2025. Third hike:
$12.99 for the Basic individual plan.
The Family plan jumped to $19.99.
The Duo plan went to $17.99.
And they introduced a new tier, Spotify Basic,
$10.99, which is literally just the
old plan repackaged as the cheap option, so they could pretend
they still offered something under $12. That's not a price
increase. That's a psychological trick. They raised
your price, took away audiobooks from the cheap tier,
and then sold you back the version of the plan you used to have for
a dollar more than you used to pay for it. And Wall Street called it
brilliant. 2026. 4th hike.
Spotify Premium is now $14.99 for
individuals in several markets. The family plan is touching
$22. The full premium tier with audiobooks,
lossless, which still doesn't exist, by the way, we'll get to that,
and the new video features is on track to hit $16.99.
Do the math with me. From 2014 to 2021,
the price never moved. From 2023 to 2026,
the price went up 4 times. You are now paying 50% more
for Spotify than you were 3 years ago. 50%!
Has the product gotten 50% better? Have they added 50%
more music? No. The catalog was already 100
million songs. It's now 110 million. That's 10%
growth, and most of the new 10 million are AI-generated noise.
We'll get to that, too. Has the audio quality improved?
No. Spotify still streams at the exact same Ogg Vorbis
bitrate it streamed at in 2020. Apple Music streams lossless.
Tidal streams hi-res. YouTube Music is catching up.
Spotify is the only major streaming service that does not offer
lossless audio in the year 2026, 5 years
after they announced it. Have the artists gotten 50% more money? Definitely not.
Per-stream payouts have gone down. We'll cover the exact numbers
in a second. So you pay 50% more. The product is the same.
The artists are paid less. Where did the money go? 2 places.
Spotify's profit margin which went from negative in 2022
to over a b— billion dollars in 2024. And Daniel
Ek's bank account, which we'll get to at the end. Right now,
just hold on to that number. 50% more.
For nothing. But that's the price hike story.
The artist payout story is worse. Here's the number Spotify
wants you to remember: $10 billion. In 2024,
Spotify announced it had paid $10 billion to the music
industry in a single year. Cumulative total since launch: nearly
$50 billion. They put it in a press release. They put
it in their investor call. They put a giant infographic on their blog.
Spotify has now paid the music industry nearly $50
billion. That sounds incredible, right?
Wrong. Let me tell you what that number actually means, because Spotify
is very deliberately not telling you. Paid to the
music industry does not mean paid to artists. The music industry is a chain.
Spotify pays the money to a distributor, DistroKid,
TuneCore, CD Baby, or directly to a major label.
The distributor or label takes their cut, usually 20-30%.
Then the label takes another cut, if there's a label involved,
usually 50-85% of what's left.
Then the publisher takes a cut. Then the songwriter gets a sliver.
Then, finally, the artist gets paid. If there's anything left.
Which there usually isn't. That $10 billion headline?
It's the top-line number, before every middleman in the chain takes
a bite. The amount that actually hits an artist's bank account is
a fraction of a fraction of a fraction. Now let's talk per
stream. The widely cited industry estimate for Spotify's
per-stream payout is between 3/10 of a cent and 5/10
of a cent. 3 tenths of a cent to one half of a cent per
stream. To make minimum wage in the United States, $15 an
hour, which is itself a low bar, an artist would need roughly
4,000 streams per hour. To make the average American salary
of about $59,000, an artist would need around 20
million streams in a year. 20 million. For context,
the average song on Spotify gets about 30 streams per
month. Not 30,000. 30. If you're a normal
independent artist with a small but loyal audience,
say 2,000 monthly listeners, which is actually pretty good for
an indie, you are generating something like 60,000 streams a
month. At 3/10 of a cent per stream, that's $180
a month. Before distributor fees. Before label cuts.
Before taxes. $180 for
a month of work that probably took a year to make. And it
gets worse. Because Spotify doesn't pay a flat rate per stream.
The payout is determined by something called the revenue share model.
Here's how it actually works. Every month,
Spotify pools all of its subscription revenue from every country.
They take their cut, roughly 30%, off the top.
Then they divide what's left by the total number of streams across
the entire platform, weighted by where those streams came
from. A stream from a US subscriber is worth
more than a stream from a Brazilian subscriber because the
US subscriber pays more. So your payout per
stream isn't 3 tenths of a cent. It's 3 tenths of a cent if your
listeners are in the US. It's 1 tenth of a cent
if they're in India. It's 7 hundredths of a cent if they're in Nigeria.
It's 5 tenths of a cent if they're in Norway. The same song,
the same stream, the same artist, the same 3
minutes and 47 seconds of music worth different amounts of money depending
on which country the listener happens to be in when they hit play.
That's why the per-stream number you see quoted is an average.
A meaningless average. Some artists make half a cent per
stream, some make a tenth of a cent. Spotify knows
this, they've known it for years. They've done nothing to fix it,
Because the ambiguity benefits them. If nobody knows exactly
what a stream is worth, nobody can prove they're being underpaid.
And they are being underpaid. By every possible measure. In 2014,
the per-stream payout was around 7 tenths of a cent.
Today, it's 3 tenths of a cent. In a decade, the value
of a single stream has dropped by more than half. And in that
same decade, Spotify's revenue has more than tripled. From $5
billion in 2019 to over $15 billion in 2024.
The pie got 3 times bigger. The slice that goes to artists
got twice as small. That's not a market correction.
That's a structural feature. Spotify has engineered their payout
system so that as the company grows, artists get less. On purpose.
You'd think a company that just announced record profits would share the love.
Right? Wrong. They announced a new rule instead. And it
might be the worst one yet. Every dollar you pay Spotify gets
split. Here's the rough breakdown: roughly 30 cents
goes to Spotify. That's their revenue. Their cut. Their fee for running the
platform. Out of that 30 cents, Spotify pays for servers,
bandwidth, app development, marketing,
podcasts, which we'll get to, and increasingly, AI features
that nobody asked for. The other 70 cents goes to rights holders.
Labels, distributors, publishers, and eventually,
maybe, artists. But that 70 cents doesn't get
split equally. It gets split based on market share. Which means Universal
Music Group, the largest label in the world, gets a much bigger chunk
than an independent artist on DistroKid. Even if
the independent artist generates the same number of streams
as a Universal artist, the Universal artist gets paid more per
stream. Because Universal has negotiated a better deal. This is
the part nobody explains to you when you sign up to put your music on
Spotify. The major labels get minimum revenue guarantees.
They get advances. They get marketing credits. They get preferential playlist
placement. The independent artist gets the standard rate,
minus distribu— distributor fees, minus whatever the distributor's
payment processor charges, minus whatever the bank charges
to convert the currency. A major label artist might see something like 5/10
of a cent per stream after everyone takes their cut. An independent
artist might see 1/10 of a cent. Same platform, same listener,
same 3-minute song. 5 times difference in payout.
Because the system isn't designed to reward streams.
It's designed to reward scale. And there's another wrinkle.
Spotify has been pushing what they call Discovery Mode.
Here's the pitch. As an artist, you can opt into
Discovery Mode on a track, and Spotify will algorithmically boost
that track in playlists and radio stations. More reach,
more streams, more listeners. Sounds great. The catch?
If you opt in, you agree to accept a lower royalty rate on streams
of that track. Spotify doesn't tell you exactly how much lower.
They just say it's a promotional royalty rate.
Translation: you pay Spotify to promote your song, by accepting less money
per stream. This is, by any reasonable definition,
payola. Payola, the practice of paying a
radio station to play your song, was made illegal in the United States in 1960.
After a massive congressional investigation. Spotify reinvented
payola, made it algorithmic, called it Discovery Mode.
And nobody sued them. Because the legal definition of payola involves
a direct payment. Discovery Mode isn't a direct payment.
It's a discounted royalty. Loophole closed. Loophole immediately
reopened. Major labels use Discovery Mode freely.
They have the volume to absorb the lower rate.
Independent artists who use it end up paying Spotify to promote
their own music, and the royalty hit can wipe out most of what they
earn from the boosted streams. So, the system looks like this: Spotify
takes 30% off the top. Then the major labels negotiate better
rates. Then the major labels use Discovery Mode to boost their artists
into your Discover Weekly and Release Radar playlists. Then those
artists get more streams, which gives the major labels
more market share. Which gives them an even bigger chunk of the
next month's pool. The flywheel spins in one direction.
Toward Universal, Sony, and Warner. Always, and every
quarter, Spotify announces record revenue.
And every quarter independent artists make less per stream than
the quarter before. And every quarter somebody at Spotify writes a
blog post about how the company is democratizing music.
Democratizing. That word. I don't think it means
what they think it means. Now, let's talk about the artists who actually
quit. Because some of them have, and the ones who haven't are
about to. In November 2023, Spotify quietly
announced a change to their royalty system. Quietly is the operative word.
It wasn't a press release. It wasn't an email to artists.
It was a blog post on a Spotify for Artists subdomain, written in
the driest corporate language possible, dropped on a Friday afternoon. Which,
as anyone in PR knows, is the day you announce things you
want people to ignore. Here's the rule: Starting in early
2024, any track that doesn't reach 1,000 streams
in a 12-month period earns zero royalties. Zero.
Not less. Spotify framed this as a fight against fraud. They said
there were tens of millions of tracks on the platform generating
tiny amounts of money— fractions of a cent— and that those
tracks were clogging up the system. By zeroing them
out, they said, they could redirect that money to working artists.
Sounds reasonable, right? Wrong.
Here's what they didn't tell you. Roughly 2/3 of the tracks on Spotify,
somewhere around 65 to 70 million songs,
get fewer than 1,000 streams per year. That's not a fringe
group of noise tracks. That's the majority of the catalog.
Independent artists, local bands, composers,
producers, bedroom musicians. The people Spotify claims
to champion. Under the old system, those tracks collectively generated something
like $40 million $40 million a year. Not a lot per artist,
but it was real money. A few hundred bucks for an indie musician is groceries.
It's a guitar string change. It's gas to drive to the next
gig. Spotify took that $40 million and redistributed it.
Not to working artists. To the major labels.
Here's how the redistribution actually works. The money saved
from the demonetized tracks goes back into the revenue share
pool. That pool is then divided based on total market
share. And who has the biggest market share on Spotify?
Universal, Sony, and Warner. The big 3.
Together they control roughly 70% of all streams on the platform.
So when Spotify redistributes the demonetized track money,
70 cents of every dollar goes to the 3 companies
that already make more money from music than anyone else
on Earth. Spotify didn't fight fraud. They took money from the bottom
of the pyramid and gave it to the top. And then they called it artist-friendly?
The independent artist, who had a song that got 800 streams last
year, used to make about $3 from that song. Now they
make zero. The major label artist whose song got a billion
streams makes slightly more. The indie artist doesn't get to
complain because, well, $3 wasn't exactly
life-changing, was it? That's the trick. The amount per
artist is small enough that no individual artist can justify
hiring a lawyer. Multiply that by millions of artists,
and you've got a massive transfer of wealth from the people who need it to
the people who already have it. And there's a second-order effect
that's even uglier. The 1,000-stream threshold has created
an incentive to cheat. If you're an artist and your track is sitting at
800 streams in November? What do you do? You buy streams.
You hire a bot farm. You pay a service in Eastern Europe
to push you over the line. Spotify created the demonetization rule,
and in doing so, they created the streaming fraud industry.
Which we'll get to in a minute. But first, let's talk about the artists
this rule was supposed to help. The working musicians.
The middle class of music. Because they're the ones getting squeezed
the hardest. And they're disappearing. Here's a question.
When was the last time a brand new artist, someone you'd never
heard of, with no label, no TikTok viral moment,
no industry connection, blew up on Spotify and became a star?
Take your time, I'll wait. You're probably thinking of Chance the Rapper.
He was the indie success story. Self-released, no label,
won a Grammy, streaming only. That was 2016.
Almost a decade ago. Since then? Crickets. The middle class
of music has been hollowed out so completely that the term doesn't even apply
anymore. There are now essentially 2 kinds of musicians on Spotify.
At the top, you have the megastars. Taylor,
Drake, Bad Bunny, The Weeknd, Billie. They make
millions from streaming because they generate billions of streams. They play the
game at a scale where the per-stream rate doesn't matter.
Even at 3 tenths of a cent, a billion streams is $3
million. They're fine. At the bottom, you have the hobbyists.
People who make music in their bedrooms, upload it to Spotify via DistroKid,
share it with their friends, and don't expect to make money.
For them, Spotify is just a place to host their music.
They're not trying to make a living. They're fine too. The middle is gone.
The working musician, the person who tours,
sells merch, has a real but modest fan base,
maybe 20,000 to 100,000 monthly listeners.
That person cannot survive on streaming revenue. The math doesn't work.
Here's a real example. In 2024, an artist named
Maria Zardoya, who fronts The Marias,
a successful indie band with hundreds of thousands of monthly listeners,
a Grammy nomination, real fans, real touring,
posted her streaming numbers. Hundreds of millions of streams across
platforms. Total revenue: enough to live on, barely,
if you split it 4 ways between band members and a manager and an agent
and don't count the cost of actually making the music. She's one
of the lucky ones. She has a label. She has fans.
She tours. Now imagine an artist with a tenth of her
audience. 200,000 monthly listeners. That's a successful
artist by indie standards. At 3 tenths of a cent per
stream, 200,000 monthly listeners generating maybe 600,000
streams a month, that's roughly $1,800. Before label cut,
before manager cut, before agent, before taxes,
after everyone takes their piece, the artist takes home maybe
$600, $600 a month. From a song catalog
that took years to build, that hundreds of thousands of people listen to
every month. That's not a career. That's a hobby that
happens to pay for itself. This is why the middle class of
music is collapsing. Not because people don't care about music
anymore. They care more than ever. Music consumption is at an
all-time high. Spotify users stream over a billion hours of music
every single day. People love music. They just don't pay
for it in a way that lets musicians live. And here's the structural
reason. In the old model— CDs, vinyl, even iTunes— if
you bought an album, the artist got a meaningful chunk of that sale. $10 for
a CD, the artist might get a dollar, maybe 2, but it was a
dollar. A real dollar. A complete transaction.
You bought the album, they got paid. In the streaming model,
that same $10 gets split across thousands of artists
based on what you listened to that month. If you listened to one artist
all month, That artist gets your share of the pool.
If you listen to 1,000, each one gets a sliver. The artist
who made your favorite album of the year? They get fractions of a cent from
you, even though you love their work. Because the system doesn't
care what you love. It cares what you played. And the industry knows
this. That's why tours have gotten more expensive.
Why merch costs more. Why artists sell
their catalogs for hundreds of millions to private equity.
Streaming doesn't pay, so every other revenue stream has
to compensate. The concert ticket that used to cost $40
now costs $120 because the artist can't
make rent from Spotify plays. You think Ticketmaster is the
bad guy. And they are. But Ticketmaster is a symptom. Spotify is
the disease. When the world's largest music platform pays
artists 3/10 of a cent per stream,
every other part of the music industry has to extract more
from you to make up the difference. The middle class of music is dying
in front of us. Quietly. Without protest.
Because the artist who would protest can't afford to take a year off to organize.
They're too busy trying to pay rent. And Spotify's response?
They raised the price of Premium again. And introduced a new feature
called, I'm not making this up, AI DJ. But before
we get to the AI slop, let's talk about the fraud economy Spotify's
own rules created. Because that's the next domino. In January 2024,
Spotify removed a song called Heat of the Moment by an artist named
Antonio Lulic. Or rather, they removed billions of streams from
him. Specifically, they accused him of using bots to
inflate his play counts and stripped him of around 700
million streams. He wasn't alone. In late 2023 and
throughout 2024, Spotify went on a purge.
They removed millions of tracks and billions of streams from artists they
accused of streaming fraud. They published a loud-and-clear report claiming
they'd identified and stopped hundreds of millions of dollars in fraudulent
payouts. Sounds great, right?
Spotify fighting fraud. Protecting artists wrong.
Here's the part they don't put in the press release: Spotify created
the fraud problem. The fraud exists because Spotify's payout system
rewards streams above all else. If streams are money,
then fake streams are fake money. And fake money
is, in any system with a leak, going to be manufactured. The bot
farm industry is now worth an estimated hundreds of millions of dollars per
year. There are services, legal services, operating openly,
advertising on Google, that will sell you 10,000 Spotify streams
for around $10. They use networks of compromised
devices, fake accounts, and residential IP proxies
to generate streams that look real to Spotify's detection
systems. An artist who's 800 streams short of the demonetization
threshold can pay $15 and cross the line. A label
trying to push a new single up the charts can buy half a million streams
for a few thousand dollars and trigger algorithmic momentum
that generates real streams. This isn't a fringe
problem. Spotify themselves estimated that somewhere
between 2 and 4% of all streams on the platform are
fake. That's billions of streams per month.
And the actual number is almost certainly higher.
Because Spotify's detection is— charitably— mediocre.
Independent analyses have put the fraud rate closer to 10%.
Here's what that means in dollar terms. If Spotify pays
out around $9 billion a year to rights holders, and even
5% of streams are fraudulent, that's roughly $450
million per year. Going to fake artists, fake labels,
and the bot farms that serve them. $450 million that
should've gone to real musicians making real music.
And here's the kicker: that money comes out of the same revenue
share pool as everyone else's. Every fake stream
is a fraction of a cent stolen from a real artist. When a bot farm
generates a million streams for a fake artist, that million
streams' worth of money is deducted from the pool that would have gone
to legitimate artists. Spotify knows this.
They've known it for years. They periodically announce crackdowns,
like the 2024 purge, to make it look
like they're doing something. But the structural problem is theirs to
solve, and they haven't solved it because solving it would require either
dramatically improving their detection technology, which costs money,
or fundamentally changing the payout model away from pure per-stream
revenue share, which would upset the major labels who benefit
from the current system. So instead, they publish an annual report,
purge a few scapegoats, and move on. There's another layer to this.
Some of the streaming fraud isn't even fraud. It's just
artists asking their fans to stream their music. Spotify's terms
of service prohibit artificial streaming, But the line between artificial
and organic is blurry. If an artist tells their fans
to put their album on repeat while they sleep, is that artificial?
If a fan runs a playlist on shuffle for 16 hours a day to support
their favorite band, is that artificial? Spotify says yes,
sometimes. They've flagged legitimate fan streaming as fraud
and pulled royalties from artists who did nothing wrong. So you have real
fraud going unpunished at scale, Real artists being punished
for fake fraud, and a payout system that incentivizes the whole
mess. Spotify's response is to raise prices and
add AI features. We're gonna talk about those AI features next.
Because they are something else. Every single day,
Spotify adds over 100,000 new tracks to its catalog.
100,000. Every day. That's more than one new
song per second. 24 hours a day, 7 days a week.
Do you know how many of those songs are made by humans playing instruments in
rooms? Nobody does. Spotify doesn't track
it. But independent estimates suggest that somewhere between 20% and 40%
of new uploads are now generated, at least in part, by AI.
Either fully AI-generated music, AI-assisted music
where the human role is essentially pressing generate, or AI-modified
existing music— sped up, Slowed down, remixed,
uploaded under fake artist names to siphon streams. Here's how the scam
works. Someone, usually operating out of a country with low labor
costs, uses an AI music generator like Suno or Udio to produce
hundreds of songs per day. These songs are not good. They're not meant
to be good. They're meant to be just good enough to slip into a mood
playlist. Lo-fi study beats.
Focus instrumental. Sleep sounds. Chill acoustic background.
You've seen these playlists, you've probably listened to them.
You didn't notice the artist names because you weren't paying attention. You just
wanted something in the background while you worked. The operator uploads
all 100 songs to Spotify under different fake artist
names. They create their own playlists, or pay
for placement on existing ones, and slot their AI tracks into
the rotation. Then they sit back and collect fractions of a cent per stream.
Multiplied by thousands of tracks, multiplied by millions
of playlist listeners. At scale, this is real money. A single
operator running 50 fake artist accounts, each generating
100,000 streams per month, is making something
like $7,500 a month. Per operator.
There are now thousands of these operators. The economics are too good to ignore.
And it gets worse. Spotify itself has been caught
doing this. In 2024, multiple investigations
revealed that Spotify's own editorial playlists, the ones
curated by Spotify staff, the ones that can make or
break a real artist's career, were stuffed with tracks from so-called
ghost artists. Artists with no online presence, no social
media, no concerts, no photos, no biography.
Just a name, a generic profile picture, and dozens of
tracks pumping into playlists with millions of followers. Why would Spotify
do this? Because they pay themselves for those streams.
The tracks are uploaded through distributors that Spotify either
owns or has financial relationships with. When Spotify's
editorial team places a ghost artist track in a flagship playlist,
the payout for that stream goes back to Spotify's bottom
line. They're laundering their own royalty payments. Spotify denied this,
of course. They said the artists were real, just private.
They said the tracks were licensed. They refused to name the artists.
They refused to provide evidence. They just denied,
and then quietly removed some of the most obvious offenders from their playlists,
and waited for the story to die. The result of all of this
is that Spotify is, increasingly, not a music streaming
service. It's an AI slop distribution platform
with a music streaming service attached. The real artists are competing
for attention against an infinite flood of machine-generated
noise. The payout pool is being drained by bad actors.
The editorial playlists that used to be a path to discovery
for real artists are increasingly populated by ghost
tracks. And here's the most insidious part. The flood of new tracks,
100,000 per day, mostly garbage, is used
by Spotify as a marketing talking point. Over 100,000 new
songs added every day, they say. The largest catalog
in music history. Yes. The largest catalog in music
history. Most of it trash. Most of it not made by humans.
Most of it never listened to by anyone. You're paying for that. Your subscription
fee is paying for the storage, the bandwidth, the algorithmic overhead
of cataloging and processing 100,000 new songs per day,
of which maybe 1% will ever be played by a real
person. The other 99% is digital pollution.
And Spotify counts it as a feature. If that makes you angry,
wait until you hear what they spent a billion dollars on next. In February
2019, Spotify bought Gimlet Media for $230
million. And Anchor, a podcast hosting platform,
for $150 million. Total: just
under $400 million. In one day to
enter the podcast business. This was the start of what would become a
billion-dollar bet. Over the next 4 years, Spotify spent
over a billion dollars acquiring podcast companies and
signing exclusive deals. They bought The Ringer from Bill Simmons
for nearly $200 million. They signed
Joe Rogan to a multi-year exclusive deal reportedly worth
over $200 million. Later renewed for a reported
$250 million. They signed
Meghan Markle to a deal reportedly worth $20 million,
which produced 12 episodes and then collapsed in mutual recrimination.
They signed the Obamas. They signed Kim Kardashian.
They bought Parcast. They bought Megaphone. They built a
podcast empire. The strategy made sense on paper. Spotify wanted
to be the default audio platform. Not just music— audio.
And podcasts had something music didn't: music royalties ate
most of the revenue. Podcasts were much cheaper. If Spotify
owned the podcast, they didn't have to share the revenue with labels.
They could keep it all. And podcasts had something else:
they were engaged. People who listened to podcasts listened for
hours per week. Habitual, loyal, captivated. If Spotify
could own that engagement, they'd own the listener. So they spent.
And spent. And spent. And it didn't work.
Here's what happened. Joe Rogan's exclusive deal drove some listeners
to Spotify. But many of his fans, the ones who already used
Apple Podcasts or other apps, resented being forced to switch.
A meaningful chunk of his audience just stopped listening rather
than migrate. And then, when Spotify's exclusivity
period ended, and Rogan went back to being available everywhere,
the supposed benefit of the exclusive deal evaporated.
Spotify paid a quarter of a billion dollars for temporary exclusivity
that didn't even last the full contract. Meghan Markle's deal produced
a single season of a podcast called Archetypes,
which got middling reviews and then was unceremoniously
dumped when the deal fell apart. She and Spotify's executive
allegedly didn't get along. A Spotify executive publicly
called her and Harry grifters. That's a Spotify executive
talking about Spotify's own signing. That's how well that
billion dollars was spent. The ringer has been successful in some
respects. Bill Simmons is a shrewd operator. But it hasn't moved the
needle for Spotify's bottom line. Gimlet, which was supposed
to be the HBO of podcasts, has been largely gutted.
Several of their flagship shows were canceled, Talented producers left.
The promise of high-quality narrative podcasting was sacrificed
on the altar of engagement metrics. And then, there's the broader
strategic failure. Spotify tried to make podcasting work
the way music works— centralized, algorithmic,
exclusive. But podcasting was built on RSS— open,
distributed, platform-agnostic. Listeners had a habit of
using whatever app they preferred. Apple Podcasts,
Overcast, Pocket Casts. They didn't want to be locked into Spotify.
And creators didn't want to be locked in either. The Joe Rogan
exclusivity backfired because creators saw what happened
when you signed with Spotify. You got paid, but you lost
your audience. By 2023, Spotify was quietly retreating
from podcasting. They canceled shows. They laid off staff,
including a significant portion of their podcast division.
They shut down Parcast. They took shows off exclusive.
They restructured their deals. They wrote down the value of
their podcast acquisitions. Meaning, in plain
English, they admitted they overpaid. Here's the brutal truth: Spotify
spent over a billion dollars to enter a business that, even at its peak,
contributed only a small fraction of their revenue.
The podcast business still doesn't generate meaningful profit
for Spotify. And in the process, they alienated listeners
who didn't want to switch apps, alienated creators who didn't
want to be locked in, and burned through capital that could have
gone to— oh, I don't know— paying artists
more. But the billion dollars is gone. The shows
are canceled. The deals have been restructured. And Spotify has
moved on to their next pivot: audiobooks. Oh,
audiobooks. Where do I even start with audiobooks? In late
2023, Spotify announced that Premium subscribers would get
15 hours of audiobooks per month included with their subscription.
Great news, right? Audible charges $15 a
month for one credit. Spotify is throwing audiobooks into your existing
subscription. What's not to like? Here's what's not to like:
15 hours. Per month. That's it. A typical audiobook
is 10 to 15 hours. So you get one audiobook per
month, maybe 2 short ones if you're lucky. After that, you have to buy more,
and the buying more is where it gets ugly. When you run out of your
15 hours, Spotify prompts you to buy more hours.
They sell 10-hour top-ups for around $13,
which is, conveniently, almost exactly what Audible charges for
a credit. So Spotify didn't replace Audible. They created a
worse Audible, with a worse selection, baked into your music
subscription. But here's the real trick. The reason Spotify added
audiobooks wasn't to give you a feature. It was to justify
the price hike. Remember the April 2024 hike? From $10.99
to $11.99? Spotify explicitly cited
the inclusion of audiobooks as the reason. They added a feature
most users don't use, and then used that feature as the justification to
raise prices on everyone. Including the people who don't use
it. It's a textbook bundling trick. You add a low-value component
to a bundle, raise the price of the bundle, and pocket the difference
from the users who never use the new component. Most Spotify subscribers
don't listen to audiobooks. Spotify knows this.
But they get to charge everyone an extra dollar or 2 per month because
the feature is included. And the audiobook selection
itself is rough. Spotify has around 250,000
audiobooks. Audible has over 700,000.
The Spotify catalog is missing huge numbers of major titles.
You'll search for a book you want, find it's not there, and be told
to either buy it separately at full retail price, or wait for Spotify
to maybe add it eventually. And the authors are getting screwed too.
In 2024, the Authors Guild and several prominent
authors filed formal complaints against Spotify
over the audiobook bundling. The issue was this: Spotify was
paying audiobook royalties based on a formula that essentially
treated audiobook listening as a fraction of total listening time,
similar to how music royalties work. But audiobooks
aren't music. A typical audiobook listener spends hours
on a single book. The way Spotify's payout math worked,
authors were getting fractions of a cent per hour of listening, which translated
to tiny, tiny payouts. For a book that took an author years
to write, and that the audiobook narrator spent weeks
recording, the royalty payout under Spotify's system might
be a few dollars for thousands of listening hours. Audible pays
authors a flat, credit-based royalty that's much more generous.
Spotify's system is by comparison an insult. And there's another
wrinkle. Spotify acquired Findaway,
an audiobook distribution platform, in 2022. That gave
them access to a huge catalog of audiobooks. But it also gave
them leverage to dictate terms to authors and narrators.
Findaway narrators, who are paid a flat fee to record books,
found that their work was being used to drive Spotify
subscriptions without any meaningful additional compensation.
The narrator who spent 40 hours recording a book might see $10
in additional royalties from Spotify's bundling, while Spotify
used their work as a marketing talking point to justify
a price hike. So let's recap. Spotify added
audiobooks to justify a price increase. Most subscribers don't
use the audiobook feature. The audiobook selection is much
smaller than Audible's. Authors get paid less under Spotify's system
than under Audible's. Narrators get paid almost
nothing extra. And Spotify gets to keep the additional revenue from
the price hike bundling. They call it bundling.
I have a different word for it. But you've probably noticed something.
I keep mentioning that Spotify still doesn't have lossless audio.
Let's talk about that broken promise next. Because it's been
5 years. In February 2021,
Spotify announced Spotify HiFi. The pitch was
simple: lossless, CD-quality audio for premium subscribers.
Higher bitrate, better sound, no compression artifacts.
Coming later in 2021. It's 2026.
HiFi still doesn't exist. 5 years. 5 years
of a promised feature that has never shipped. Spotify has mentioned HiFi in
exactly zero product launches since the original
announcement. They've removed references to it from their website.
They've stopped responding to questions about it. Their customer
support, when asked, gives vague non-answers like,
we're still exploring options. In the same 5 years that Spotify
has failed to ship lossless audio, Apple Music shipped it.
For free. Included in the standard subscription.
No extra charge. Tidal built their entire brand
around it. Amazon Music Unlimited added it at no extra cost.
YouTube Music added it. Qobuz has had it for a decade. Every major
music streaming service on Earth offers lossless audio. Except Spotify.
Why? Here's the honest answer: Spotify can't afford to ship
it. Not because lossless audio is expensive. It isn't,
not really. The bandwidth costs are manageable.
But because Spotify's entire infrastructure was built around aggressive
audio compression. Their Ogg Vorbis codec at 96
to 320 kilobits per second was designed to minimize bandwidth costs
at scale. Serving billions of streams per day at 320
kilobits per second costs them a certain amount of money. Serving those same streams
at 1.4 megabits, CD quality, would cost them roughly
4 times as much in bandwidth. And Spotify operates on thin
margins. Or at least, they claim to. The other reason is
strategic. Spotify's not stupid. They know
that if they ship lossless audio, they need to either charge more
for it, which would mean another price hike, which would mean another round
of bad press, or include it in the existing plan,
which would mean absorbing the bandwidth cost. So they've stalled.
They announced HiFi in 2021, to keep up with Apple's
announcement that Apple Music was going lossless.
They never had to ship it because their subscribers didn't
leave in meaningful numbers. Most people can't tell the
difference between 320 kbps and lossless on
Bluetooth earbuds anyway. So Spotify quietly killed
the project and never told anyone. But the promise is still out there.
The 2021 announcement is still in archives. People still
ask about HiFi in Spotify community forums.
Spotify still ignores them. 5 years. This is the kind of
small, specific, infuriating failure that defines modern Spotify.
It's not a single catastrophic mistake. It's a thousand small ones.
A promised feature that never shipped. A price hike that wasn't justified.
A royalty cut disguised as fraud prevention. A podcast
empire that collapsed. An audiobook pivot that nobody asked for.
Each one, in isolation, is a minor story.
Together they form a pattern. And the pattern is this: Spotify
takes more from you, gives less to artists, and invests the difference
in whatever the next big pivot is supposed to be. Podcasts,
audiobooks, AI. Anything except the core product,
the music app you pay for, but maybe you don't care about hi-fi.
Maybe you don't care about podcasts. Maybe you just want to know why
your Discover Weekly has gotten worse. Let's talk about
that. When was the last time Discover Weekly introduced you
to an artist you'd never heard of, who you actually loved,
who you then went and followed, and whose music you then sought out on
your own? Take your time. For most of you, the answer is,
I can't remember. Maybe years ago. Maybe never.
Here's why. When Discover Weekly launched in 2015,
It was genuinely magical. The algorithm would analyze your
listening history, find patterns, and recommend songs from artists
you'd never heard but who matched your taste. People would post their Discover
Weekly on social media. It was a feature. A real feature.
Something Spotify did that nobody else could do.
Fast forward to 2026. Discover Weekly is mostly the
same songs you already listen to, Slightly remixed,
with one or two unfamiliar tracks buried at the bottom. Release Radar
is dominated by major label releases. Your daily mixes have
devolved into the same 50 songs on rotation.
Spotify's algorithmic recommendations have, by almost every user's
anecdotal experience, gotten worse. Why? Here's the structural
reason: Spotify's recommendation algorithm isn't purely
designed to find you new music you'd love. It's designed to maximize total
listening time. Those sound like the same goal. They're not.
If Spotify wanted to find you new music you'd love, they'd recommend
unfamiliar tracks and accept that some of those wouldn't click,
leading you to skip, leading to a temporary dip in engagement.
They don't do that. Instead, the algorithm plays it safe.
It recommends tracks similar to what you already listen to, Because those
tracks have a high probability of being played through
to the end. More plays through to the end means more listening time,
more streams, more revenue. The algorithm is optimizing for engagement,
not discovery. And engagement on a per-user basis is
maximized by playing it safe. There's also the editorial layer.
Spotify's editorial playlists— Rap Caviar, Today's Top
Hits, Hot Country, Rock Classics— are curated by Spotify staff.
But those staff are heavily influenced by major label priorities.
Major labels have teams whose entire job is to pitch Spotify
editors for playlist placement. They send gifts, they have
relationships, they have leverage. Independent artists don't
have any of that. So the playlists that drive discovery are dominated
by major label artists. The algorithmic playlists are
tuned for engagement rather than discovery. And the long
tail of independent music, which Spotify claims to champion,
is buried under a pile of major label priorities and
safe recommendations. And then there's Discovery Mode, which we covered earlier.
The payola scheme. Major labels can opt their tracks
into Discovery Mode, accept a lower royalty rate, and get algorithmic
boosts. Independent artists can technically do the same,
but the lower royalty rate, hurts them disproportionately.
The result? The algorithm is even more skewed toward major label
artists, because they're the ones who can afford to pay for placement.
There's another problem. Spotify's algorithm has a feedback loop
problem. If you listen to a track once, even accidentally, even because
you skipped to it, the algorithm treats that as a positive signal.
It then recommends more tracks like that, which you might
listen to, which reinforces the signal, which leads to
more recommendations of the same kind. Your recommendations can drift
in directions you never intended, based on a single accidental listen.
This is why your daily mix sometimes looks like it belongs to a
completely different person. The algorithm got confused by a stray listen
and decided you must be a fan of, I don't know, German techno.
And now you can't get rid of it. And Spotify
doesn't give you good tools to fix this. There's no reset my
recommendations button. There's no I don't like this button on
the home screen the way there is on YouTube. You can block an artist,
but you can't tell the algorithm why you didn't like a particular
track. You're stuck with what it thinks of you. The fundamental issue is
that Spotify's algorithm isn't working for you. It's working
for Spotify. Its job is to maximize your listening
time, which maximizes their revenue, which they then use
to pay artists less per stream while raising your subscription price.
The algorithm is a machine for extracting value from your attention.
It just happens to play music while it does it. You'd think,
given all of this, that Spotify would at least be cheap.
Right? Wrong. They're the most expensive mainstream music service.
And their biggest competitor pays artists twice as much per
stream. Let's talk about Apple Music. Apple Music pays
artists roughly double what Spotify pays per stream. Let me
just say that again. Apple Music pays artists roughly double what
Spotify pays per stream. The widely cited numbers are Spotify,
3/10 of a cent to 5/10 of a cent per stream. Apple Music,
7/10 of a cent to 1 cent per stream. Apple pays twice
as much. And their subscription price is, in most
markets, the same as Spotify's. Or, after Spotify's 2025
and 2026 hikes, cheaper. Why? Because Apple doesn't
need Spotify to make money. Apple makes its money selling iPhones.
Apple Music exists to make the iPhone ecosystem more attractive.
It's a value-add, a loss leader in some quarters.
Apple can afford to pay artists more per stream because Apple
doesn't need Apple Music to be massively profitable on
its own. Own. The profitability comes from the iPhone you bought
to use Apple Music on. Spotify, on the other hand, is just
Spotify. They don't sell phones, they don't sell laptops,
they don't have a hardware business subsidizing their software business.
Every dollar Spotify pays to artists is a dollar
that doesn't go to Spotify's profit margin. So they squeeze. And it's not
just the per-stream payout. Apple Music has shipped feature after
feature that Spotify hasn't. Lossless audio, Spatial audio with
Dolby Atmos. Lyrics that scroll in real time. Live lyrics
that you can sing along to. Apple Music Sing, which lets you mute the vocals
and karaoke any song. All included in the base subscription.
All free. Spotify has, in the same period, raised prices
4 times, added a podcast empire that they then had to
write down, forced an audiobook bundle on users
who didn't want it, and shipped an AI DJ that nobody asked
for. They have not shipped lossless. They have not shipped spatial
audio. They have not shipped Apple Music Sing, but they did add
an AI DJ. So here's the brutal competitive reality.
Spotify is being squeezed from above and below.
From above, Apple Music has the resources of Apple behind it.
Apple can outspend Spotify on licensing, on features, on marketing.
Apple can afford to ship lossless at no extra cost because
Apple can absorb the bandwidth hit. Spotify can't.
From below, YouTube Music is bundled with YouTube Premium,
which means millions of subscribers get YouTube Music essentially
for free as part of a broader subscription. Amazon Music is
bundled with Prime. Spotify is the only major music service
that has to stand on its own. This is why Spotify is raising
prices. They have no other lever. They can't subsidize from a
hardware business. They can't bundle with a broader subscription
that has nothing to do with music. They have to extract
more from their existing subscribers because their existing subscribers
are their only revenue source. And the market is noticing.
Spotify's market share in the US has been slowly eroding.
Not dramatically— they're still the largest music streaming service globally—
but the trend is concerning for them. Apple Music has
grown to around 30% market share in the US.
YouTube Music is gaining. Especially among younger users.
Amazon Music has grown thanks to Prime bundling. Spotify's growth has
slowed, and in some markets, reversed. Spotify's response
to all of this has been: more price hikes, more pivots, more AI
features. They're trying to convince Wall Street that they have a path to
continued growth, while their actual core product—
the music streaming app that you pay for— is, by every measurable
metric, getting worse. There's a question nobody at Spotify
wants to answer: if your competitors can pay artists more,
ship better features, and charge less or the same, while you raise
prices every year, ship fewer features, and pay artists less,
what exactly is your value proposition? What are you offering that
they don't? The honest answer is playlists. Spotify's playlist
curation, even after all the criticism I just gave it, is still better
than Apple Music's. And Discover Weekly, even watered down,
is still better than anything Apple offers.
Spotify's recommendation engine, despite its flaws, is still
the best in the business for surfacing music that matches your taste.
But is that enough? Is playlist curation worth paying 50% more
than you did 3 years ago? Is it worth knowing that the artists you love
are getting paid half what Apple would pay them? For most
users, the answer is yes. For now. Spotify is sticky.
Your playlists are there. Your friends are there. Your Wrapped is there.
Switching is annoying. But stickiness has limits.
And every price hike tests those limits. Let's talk about
the man running this whole show. Because his story is the most
revealing part of all of this. Daniel Ek, the founder and CEO of
Spotify, is a billionaire. He's worth something
around $5 to $7 billion depending on the day.
He founded Spotify in 2006. He's been the
CEO since the beginning. He is the company, in many ways.
In 2023, Daniel Ek started selling Spotify shares.
A lot of them. Hundreds of millions of dollars worth.
Not in a panic, not all at once, but steadily.
Through prearranged trading plans the kind executives use to cash
out without signaling that they think the stock is about to crash.
Perfectly legal. Perfectly normal. But also,
perfectly telling. What's he doing with the money? He's buying a
weapons company. Specifically, Ek has invested hundreds
of millions of euros into Helsing, a European defense AI startup that
makes AI software for fighter jets, drones, and military
applications. He's not just an investor. He's the chairman of the
board. He personally lobbied the German government on Helsing's behalf.
He has made defense tech his second full-time job.
This is not a side hobby. This is a billionaire who
built his fortune on music streaming, on the labor of millions
of artists who are paid 3 tenths of a cent per stream,
deciding that what he really wants to do with his wealth is build the
next generation of weapons systems, while the music platform that
made him rich is, by every measure, decaying.
Now, to be clear, defense technology is a legitimate
industry. Helsing is a real company doing real work that
European governments consider important, especially in the context
of the war in Ukraine. Daniel Ek is allowed to spend his money however
he wants. This is not a moral judgment on defense tech,
but it is a judgment on priorities. The founder
of the world's largest music streaming platform, a platform that has been criticized
by artists, by lawmakers, by the entire independent music
community for its treatment of musicians, has decided
that his time and money are better spent building AI for fighter jets
than fixing the company he founded. Spotify artists are
paid fractions of a cent. Spotify hasn't shipped a promised
lossless feature in 5 years. Spotify's podcast
empire collapsed. Spotify's algorithm has gotten worse.
Spotify's prices have gone up 4 times in 3 years.
And the CEO's attention is elsewhere. Ek still shows
up to earnings calls. He still gives interviews about Spotify's future.
But the energy, the focus, the obsession that built Spotify
in the first place— that's gone. He's checked out. He's the defense guy
now. Spotify is the thing that pays for Helsing.
And the stock market has noticed something different. While Ek sells,
institutional investors have been buying. Spotify's stock
has been on a tear, up over 300% from its 2022 lows.
Wall Street loves Spotify right now. They love
the price hikes. They love the margin expansion. They love the AI
narrative. They love that Ek is squeezing more profit out of every
subscriber. Wall Street doesn't care that artists are paid
less. Wall Street doesn't care that the product is getting worse. Wall Street
cares about one thing: profit growth. And Spotify is
delivering profit growth— by squeezing everyone else. So here's
where we are: the CEO is checked out. The stock is at all-time
highs. The product is decaying. Artists are paid less than
ever. Prices are higher than ever. And Wall Street is
cheering. Let's talk about that stock price. Because it's the
most revealing number of all. In early 2023,
Spotify's stock was trading at around $70 per
share. In early 2026, it's over $400.
That's a nearly sixfold increase in 3 years.
Spotify's market capitalization is now north of $80 billion.
Why? Because Spotify finally turned profitable.
After years of operating at a loss, after years of burning cash to
acquire users, build the podcast empire,
expand into new markets, Spotify started making real
money in 2024. Their operating margin went positive.
Their free cash flow exploded. They reported record profits quarter
after quarter. The stock took off. How did they turn profitable?
Not by growing subscribers. Subscriber growth has slowed.
Not by launching successful new products. The podcast
empire collapsed. Audiobooks are a niche. AI features are fluff.
They turned profitable by raising prices and cutting costs.
The prices, we've covered. 4 hikes in 3 years.
50% more revenue per subscriber. The cost cuts are less visible
but more brutal. Spotify has laid off thousands of employees
since 2023. They shut down entire divisions.
They killed shows. They restructured deals. They squeezed every
dollar out of their existing operations. And here's the
most important cost cut of all: they didn't raise artist royalties.
Per-stream payouts went down. The 1,000-stream demonetization
rule redirected money from small artists to major labels.
Discovery Mode let them pay lower rates to artists
who opted in. Every lever Spotify had to reduce the percentage of revenue
that went to artists, they pulled. The result?
Spotify's gross margin improved from around 26% in
2022 to over 30% in 2025.
That 4 percentage point improvement on a $15 billion revenue
base is $600 million in additional profit,
per year, taken directly out of the royalty pool
that should have gone to artists. So when you read that Spotify's stock
is at an all-time high, that they're more profitable than
ever, that Wall Street loves them— understand
what that means. It means they've figured out how to extract more money from
you and from artists while delivering less. That's what their profitability
is built on. Price hikes. Cost cuts. Lower royalties.
Higher margins. Wall Street is celebrating.
Artists are suffering. Listeners are paying more. The CEO
is selling shares to build weapons. The product is decaying.
This is what a successful tech company looks like in 2026.
And the most maddening part? Spotify knows.
They know the artists are unhappy. They know the listeners are frustrated.
They know the listeners are frustrated. They know the competition
is catching up. They just don't care, because the stock price is
the only metric that matters to them, and the stock price is going up.
But there's one more thing they do that I haven't covered yet. The thing
that makes everyone forgive them every December.
Wrapped. Let's talk about Wrapped. Every December,
Spotify releases Wrapped. Your year in music. Your top
artists, top songs, top genres, total minutes listened.
A slick slideshow with bright colors and shareable graphics.
Instagram fills up with Wrapped screenshots. Twitter fills up with
Wrapped screenshots. TikTok fills up with Wrapped reactions.
Wrapped is brilliant. It's the most successful marketing campaign in
music history. It turns every Spotify user into a free
billboard for Spotify. Every December, without fail.
But here's what Wrapped actually is. It's a distraction.
While you're sharing your top 5 artists, Spotify is raising
your subscription price. While you're bragging about your 100,000
minutes listened, Spotify is cutting per-stream royalties to
artists. While you're celebrating your music taste, Spotify is
shipping AI-generated slop into your playlists.
Wrapped is the dessert they serve you so you don't notice that
the main course got smaller and more expensive. And Wrapped has gotten worse
too. The 2024 Wrapped was widely criticized
for being less detailed, less interesting, less shareable
than previous years. Spotify added AI-generated
podcast commentary about your listening habits, which most users
found annoying. They removed some of the granular stats
that power users loved. They turned a beloved annual tradition into
another vehicle for their AI features. Wrapped is also,
structurally, free user research for Spotify.
Every time you share your Wrapped, you're telling Spotify,
and the world, what kind of music you like, how much you
listen, what genres you gravitate toward, how loyal you are to certain
artists. Spotify uses this data to train their recommendation
algorithms, to sell targeted advertising on the free
tier, to negotiate with major labels for better terms. You're giving
them all of that, for free, every December and
thanking them for the privilege. But here's the thing
about Wrapped. It works. People love it. They look forward
to it. They share it. They defend Spotify because of it. Wrapped is the
single best argument that Spotify still makes something people genuinely
love, which makes it hard to argue that Spotify is a bad
company. Because if they were, why would you look forward
to their annual recap so much? The answer is that Spotify isn't a
bad company. They're a good company that's been slowly,
deliberately optimizing for the wrong things.
They optimized for engagement instead of discovery. For margin instead
of artist welfare. For Wall Street instead of musicians. They didn't
become evil. They became efficient. And efficiency, when your product is
art, is corrosive. So what should you do? Let's talk
about that. So, You've listened to all of this. You've heard the numbers.
You've heard about the price hikes, the royalty cuts, the AI slop,
the podcast collapse, the audiobook bundling, the broken
hi-fi promise, the algorithmic decay, the CEO's exit, the stock
bubble. And you're wondering, should I cancel Spotify? Maybe. Here's my
honest take. Spotify is still, in many ways, the best
music streaming app. The recommendation engine, even watered down,
is the best in the business. The playlist ecosystem is unmatched.
The social features— collaborative playlists, Blend,
Wrapped— are genuinely fun. The catalog is huge. The app
works well. If you care about music discovery, Spotify is
still the easiest place to find new music. But every year, the gap
between Spotify and its competitors narrows.
Apple Music has lossless. Apple Music has spatial audio.
Apple Music pays artists twice as much. YouTube Music is bundled
with YouTube Premium. Tidal pays artists even more than Apple. Even Amazon Music
has lossless now. If you care about audio quality,
switch to Apple Music or Tidal. If you care about artist
compensation, switch to Apple Music or Tidal. If you want lossless,
switch to literally anyone else. If you're tired of price
hikes, switch to YouTube Music, which is bundled with YouTube
Premium and often effectively cheaper. If you want
the best playlist curation and the best recommendation engine,
and you're willing to pay for it, stay with Spotify. Just know what
you're paying for, and who you're paying, and what they're doing with the money.
Here's what I'd actually recommend. Don't make a moral decision.
Make a practical one. Try Apple Music for a month.
Try Tidal. See if you miss Spotify. Most people
don't miss it as much as they think they will. Your playlists can be transferred
with tools like Soundeze, and tune my music. Your friends will
still be on Spotify if you want to make collaborative playlists.
You can keep Spotify free tier for social stuff and pay
for Apple Music for actual listening. And— this is the most
important part— buy music. Buy albums on Bandcamp.
Buy vinyl. Buy merch. Go to concerts. Buy directly
from artists whenever you can. Streaming was never going to sustain
a music ecosystem. It was always going to extract from it. The only
way to actually support artists is to pay them directly,
in transactions that aren't mediated by a streaming platform's
royalty math. Spotify has a serious problem.
Their product is decaying. Their artists are starving.
Their CEO has checked out. Their stock is a bubble.
Their pivots have failed. Their promises have been broken.
Their competition is catching up. But Spotify's biggest problem
isn't any of those things. Spotify's biggest problem is
that they've forgotten what they're for. They were supposed to be the
platform that gave every artist a fair shot and every listener
access to every song ever recorded. They were
supposed to be the future of music. Instead, they've become a cautionary
tale. A story about what happens when a company that promised
to democratize an industry decides to squeeze it instead.
You've paid Spotify more money every year since 2023.
The artists you love have been paid less per stream every year since
2023. And Spotify's stock has gone up every year since 2023.
3 numbers. 3 trajectories. All connected.
You can decide for yourself what they add up to, but if you ask me,
they add up to a serious problem.